<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ScrollView
    xmlns:android="http://schemas.android.com/apk/res/android"
    android:id="@+id/scroll7"
    android:layout_height="wrap_content"
    android:layout_width="match_parent"
    android:background="@drawable/bg12">
<RelativeLayout xmlns:android="http://schemas.android.com/apk/res/android"
    xmlns:tools="http://schemas.android.com/tools" android:layout_width="match_parent"
    android:layout_height="match_parent" android:paddingLeft="@dimen/activity_horizontal_margin"
    android:paddingRight="@dimen/activity_horizontal_margin"
    android:paddingTop="@dimen/activity_vertical_margin"
    android:paddingBottom="@dimen/activity_vertical_margin"
    tools:context="com.horizon.abhijit.easycs1.chap1_mcq">

    <Spinner
        android:layout_width="match_parent"
        android:layout_height="50dp"
        android:id="@+id/spinner"
        android:layout_alignParentTop="true"
        android:layout_centerHorizontal="true"
        android:entries="@array/spinner_item1"
        android:layout_marginTop="10dp"
        android:background="@drawable/bg29" />
    <TextView
        android:layout_width="match_parent"
        android:layout_height="wrap_content"
        android:layout_below="@+id/spinner"
        android:text="Q. 1 Wave nature of light is evidenced by  \n\n          (a)Photo-electric effect  \n\n          (b)Interference  \n\n          (c)black body radiation  \n\n          (d)Nuclear emission\n\nQ. 2 Two sources are said to be coherent if their emitted waves have  \n\n          (a)same wavelength  \n\n          (b)same amplitude    \n\n          (c)constant phase difference  \n\n          (d)all the three\n\nQ. 3 When the light wave is reflected at the glass-air interface, the change of phase of thereflected wave is equal to  \n\n          (a)0   \n\n          (b)1  \n\n          (c) π/2  \n\n          (d)π\n\nQ. 4 Two waves having their intensities in the ratio 9 : 1 produce interference. In theinterference pattern the ratio of maximum to minimum intensity is equal to  \n\n          (a)2 : 1   \n\n          (b)9 : 1   \n\n          (c)3 : 1   \n\n          (d)4 : 1\n\nQ. 5 Two beams interfere have their amplitudes ratio 2 : 1. Then the intensity ratio of brightand dark fringes is  \n\n          (a)2 : 1   \n\n          (b)1 : 2  \n\n          (c)9 : 1   \n\n          (d)4 : 1\n\nQ. 6 When a thin film of oil or soap bubble is illuminated with white light, multiple coloursappear. This is due to  \n\n          (a)diffraction   \n\n          (b)polarization  \n\n          (c)total internal reflection  \n\n          (d)interference\n\nQ. 7 In interference of light which of the following statement is correct :  \n\n          (a)There is redistribution of light energy at the point of superposition.  \n\n          (b)There is addition and cancellation of light energy at the point of superposition.   \n\n          (c)There is reflection and refraction of light energy at the point of superposition.   \n\n          (d)None of these\n\nQ. 8 Condition of destructive interference is :   \n\n          (a)Path difference is even multiple of  \n\n          (b)Path difference is odd multiple of  \n\n          (c)Path difference is integral multiple of  \n\n          (d) None of the above. \n\nQ. 9 Condition of constructive interference is :   \n\n          (a)Path difference is odd multiple of  \n\n          (b)Path difference is even multiple of  \n\n          (c)Path difference is integral multiple of  \n\n          (d)None of the above\n\nQ. 10 In reflected system condition of destructive interference for their parallel films is :   \n\n          (a)2 μtcos r = (2n + 1)   \n\n          (b)2μtcos r = n λ  \n\n          (c)2μt sin r = n λ   \n\n          (d)2 μt cot r = n λ\n\nQ. 11 In transmitted system, the condition of constructive interference forthin parallel filmsis :   \n\n          (a)2 μtcos r = n λ   \n\n          (b)2μtcos r = (2n + 1)   \n\n          (c)2μtcos (r + θ )= n λ   \n\n          (d)2μtcos (r + θ ) = (2n + 1) \n\nQ. 12 Choose the correct statement from the following :   \n\n          (a)The conditions for constructive and destructive interference in reflected andtransmitted system for thin parallel films are same.   \n\n          (b)The conditions for constructive and destructive interference in reflected andtransmitted system for thin parallel films are complementary.   \n\n          (c)Only the conditions of constructive interference in reflected and transmitted system forthin parallel films are same.   \n\n          (d)None of these\n\nQ. 13 In Netwon’s rings, interference is due to light rays reflected from  \n\n          (a)lower surface of lens and upper surface of glass plate.  \n\n          (b)lower surface of glass plate and upper surface of lens.   \n\n          (c)lower surface of lens and lower surface of glass plate.   \n\n          (d)upper surface of lens and upper surface of glass plate.  \n\nQ. 14 Light waves are  \n\n          (a)longitudinal waves   \n\n          (b)transverse waves  \n\n          (c)both a and b  \n\n          (d)none of them\n\nQ. 15 Which of the followings does not support the wave nature of light ?   \n\n          (a)Interference   \n\n          (b)Polarization  \n\n          (c)Compton effect  \n\n          (d)Diffraction\n\nQ. 16 A phase difference π between two interfering beams is equivalent to path difference.   \n\n          (a)2λ   \n\n          (b)λ  \n\n          (c)λ/2  \n\n          (d)none of them\n\nQ. 17 In reflected light the central fringe of Newton’s ring is  \n\n          (a)dark  \n\n          (b)non-uniform  \n\n          (c)bright  \n\n          (d)none of them\n\nQ. 18 In Newton’s ring experiment, the diameter of bright rings is proportional to  \n\n          (a)odd natural numbers  \n\n          (b)natural numbers  \n\n          (c)even natural numbers  \n\n          (d)square root of natural numbers\n\nQ. 19 Extended source is needed in  \n\n          (a)Young’s double slit experiment   \n\n          (b)Biprism experiment  \n\n          (c)Newton’s ring experiment  \n\n          (d)none of them\n\nQ. 20 In transmitted light the central fringe of Newton’s ring is  \n\n          (a)dark   \n\n          (b)non-uniform  \n\n          (c)bright  \n\n          (d)none of them.  \n\nQ. 21 Which of the following are coherent sources ?   \n\n          (a)A 60 W and A 100 W bulbs  \n\n          (b)Two bulbs each of 60 W  \n\n          (c)Two halves of a 60 W bulbs  \n\n          (d)The virtual sources obtained by a biprism\n\nQ. 22 In interference with two coherent sources, the fringe width varies  \n\n          (a)directly with wavelength  \n\n          (b)inversely with wavelength  \n\n          (c)directly with the separation between slits  \n\n          (d)inversely with the distance between the slits and screen.  \n\nQ. 23 Interference was observed in interference chamber when air was present. Now thechamber is evacuated. And the same light is used, a careful observation will see  \n\n          (a)no interference  \n\n          (b)interference with brighter bands  \n\n          (c)interference with darker bands  \n\n          (d)interference in which width of fringes will be slightly increased. \n\nQ. 24 Interference occurs in  \n\n          (a)longitudinal wave only  \n\n          (b)transverse wave only  \n\n          (c)electromagnetic wave only   \n\n          (d)all above waves\n\nQ. 25 Oil floating on water looks coloured due to interference of light. The approximatethickness of oil for such effect to be visible is  \n\n          (a)100 Å  \n\n          (b)10,000Å  \n\n          (c)1 mm   \n\n          (d)1 cm\n\nQ. 26 Newton rings are  \n\n          (a)locus of points of equal thickness  \n\n          (b)locus of points of equal inclination  \n\n          (c)locus of points of equal inclination and thickness  \n\n          (d)neither a nor b\n\nQ. 27 In Newton’s ring arrangement the diameter of rings formed is propositional to \n\n          (a)λ   \n\n          (b)λ2  \n\n          (c)√λ  \n\n          (d)1/√λ\n\nQ. 28 In Newton’s ring arrangement with air film in reflected light the diameter of nth ring is Dn. If the air is replaced by liquid of refractive index μ, the diameter of thenth ring will become____of the original.   \n\n          (a)√μ - times   \n\n          (b) 1/√μ- times  \n\n          (c) 1/μ- times  \n\n          (d)μ - times\n\nQ. 29 One of the phenomenon which cannot be explained by the wave theory of light \n\n          (a)Polarization  \n\n          (b)Diffraction  \n\n          (c)Photo electric effect   \n\n          (d)Interference\n\nQ. 30 To demonstrate the phenomenon of interference, we require two sources which emit radiation of,   \n\n          (a)the same frequency  \n\n          (b)nearly the same frequency  \n\n          (c)the same frequency and have a definite phase relationship  \n\n          (d)the different wavelength\n\nQ. 31 Two waves of the same frequency and of the same amplitude all reaching a pointsimultaneously. What should be the phase difference between two waves so thatthe amplitude of the resultant wave be 2a ?   \n\n          (a)90°   \n\n          (b)120°   \n\n          (c)0°  \n\n          (d)180°\n\nQ. 32 Two light waves of the same intensity are interfacing. The intensity of light at brightfringe compared to the intensity of one of the waves is  \n\n          (a)two times  \n\n          (b)four times  \n\n          (c)one -fourth times   \n\n          (d)three times\n\nQ. 33 In which of the following the interference is produced by the division of wave front  \n\n          (a)Fabry-perot interferometer  \n\n          (b)Michelson’s interferometer \n\n          (c)Newton’s ring  \n\n          (d)Fresnel’s biprism\n\nQ. 34 When a thin sheet of mica is introduced in the path of one of the interfering beams,then the fringe width,   \n\n          (a)increases  \n\n          (b)decreases  \n\n          (c)remains unchanged   \n\n          (d)none of these\n\nQ. 35 In Newton’s ring arrangement, bright and dark rings are obtained using sodium yellowlight. What happens if the top surface of the glass plate on which the lens in keptis highly silvered ?   \n\n          (a)fringe width decreases  \n\n          (b)fringe width increases  \n\n          (c)fringe width remain unchanged  \n\n          (d)fringes disappear\n\nQ. 36 A wedge-shaped film is observed in reflected sunlight first through a red glass andthen through a blue glass. Number of fringes in later case is  \n\n          (a)Less  \n\n          (b)More  \n\n          (c)Equal in both cases  \n\n          (d)None of these. \n\nQ. 37 Young’s experiment proved that ______.  \n\n          (a)light consists of waves  \n\n          (b)light consists of particles  \n\n          (c)light is neither particle nor wave  \n\n          (d)light is both particle and a wave. \n\nQ. 38 Two sources of light are said to be coherent if waves produced by them have the same_______.  \n\n          (a)wavelength  \n\n          (b)amplitude  \n\n          (c)wavelength and a constant phase difference  \n\n          (d)amplitude and wavelength\n\nQ. 39 In Fresnel’s biprism experiment, the central fringe is _______.  \n\n          (a)bright  \n\n          (b)dark  \n\n          (c)first dark then bright  \n\n          (d)first bright then dark\n\nQ. 40 If Young’s apparatus be immersed in water then the fringe width _______.  \n\n          (a)increases   \n\n          (b)decreases  \n\n          (c)remains unchanged  \n\n          (d)None of these\n\nQ. 41 If Young’s interference experiment is performed using two separate identical sources of light instead of using two slits illuminated by a single source ________.  \n\n          (a)interference fringes will be brighter  \n\n          (b)interference fringes will be darker  \n\n          (c)no fringes will be obtain  \n\n          (d)number of interference fringes will increase\n\nQ. 42 When a monochromatic light is replaced by white light in Fresnel’s biprismexperiment, the central fringe is ______.  \n\n          (a)dark   \n\n          (b)white  \n\n          (c)coloured  \n\n          (d)it changes colour from violet to red\n\nQ. 43 In Newton’s rings arrangement, if the distance between the lens and the plate is increased, the order of the ring at a given point ______.  \n\n          (a)decreases  \n\n          (b)increases  \n\n          (c)remains unchanged  \n\n          (d)None of these\n\nQ. 44 In Newton’s rings experiment, bright and dark rings are obtained using sodium light. Ifthe entire set-up is dipped into water the diameters of rings _______.  \n\n          (a)increases   \n\n          (b)decreases  \n\n          (c)remains unchanged  \n\n          (d)fringe pattern disappears\n\nQ. 45 In Young’s double slit experiment, if the monochromatic source of yellow light isreplaced by red light. The fringe width  \n\n          (a)increases   \n\n          (b)decreases  \n\n          (c)unchanged  \n\n          (d)the fringes disappear\n\nQ. 46 Which will most likely occur when light passes through a double slit  \n\n          (a)Interference only   \n\n          (b)reflection  \n\n          (c)diffraction only  \n\n          (d)diffraction and interference both\n\nQ. 47 An excessively thin film appears ___ in reflected light.   \n\n          (a)White  \n\n          (b)Black   \n\n          (c)Red  \n\n          (d)Yellow\n\nQ. 48 When white light falls on very thick film which of the following statement is true :   \n\n          (a)Bright and distinct colours will appear.   \n\n          (b)It appear black in reflected system.   \n\n          (c)Only blue and red colours will appear  \n\n          (d)It will appear white in reflected system\n\nQ. 49 In Newton’s ring arrangement, if plano-convex lens is replaced by Biconvex lens,which of the following statement is true :   \n\n          (a)Width of the fringes reduced to half of its original value.   \n\n          (b)Width of the fringes increases to double of its original value. 	 \n\n          (c)Width of the fringes remains same.   \n\n          (d)None of these\n\nQ. 50 When Newon’s ring is observed under white light, which of the following statement is true :   \n\n          (a)Only first few coloured rings will be visible.   \n\n          (b)All coloured rings will be visible.   \n\n          (c)All rings will appear white.   \n\n          (d)None of the above. "
        android:textColor="#000000"
        android:textSize="15dp"
        android:id="@+id/mcq_text"
        android:paddingTop="15dp"
        android:typeface="normal" />
</RelativeLayout>
    </ScrollView>
