<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ScrollView
    xmlns:android="http://schemas.android.com/apk/res/android"
    android:id="@+id/scroll7"
    android:layout_height="wrap_content"
    android:layout_width="match_parent"
    android:background="@drawable/bg12"
    android:layout_below="@+id/scroll8">

<RelativeLayout xmlns:android="http://schemas.android.com/apk/res/android"
    xmlns:tools="http://schemas.android.com/tools" android:layout_width="match_parent"
    android:layout_height="match_parent" android:paddingLeft="@dimen/activity_horizontal_margin"
    android:paddingRight="@dimen/activity_horizontal_margin"
    android:paddingTop="@dimen/activity_vertical_margin"
    android:paddingBottom="@dimen/activity_vertical_margin"
    tools:context="com.horizon.abhijit.easycs1.chap5_mcq">

    <Spinner
        android:layout_width="match_parent"
        android:layout_height="50dp"
        android:id="@+id/spinner5"
        android:layout_alignParentTop="true"
        android:entries="@array/spinner_item5"
        android:layout_centerHorizontal="true"
        android:background="@drawable/bg29"></Spinner>
        <TextView
            android:layout_width="match_parent"
            android:layout_height="wrap_content"
           android:text="  \n\nQ.1 In a uniaxial crystal, the number of directions along which the two refracted rays travel with              \n\n          (a) Same velocity is one             \n\n          (b) Same velocities are two             \n\n          (c) Same velocities are three             \n\n          (d) none of these  \n\nQ.2 When a ray of unpolarized light is incident in a direction parallel to the optic axis of a calcite crystal then, O and E-rays travel,             \n\n          (a) Along the different directions with the same velocity             \n\n          (b) Along the same direction with same velocity             \n\n          (c) Along the same direction with different velocity.              \n\n          (d) Along the different directions with different velocities. \n\nQ.3 Unpolarized light falls on two Nicols so oriented that no light is transmitted. If a third Nicol is placed between them, not parallel to either of the two Nicols in question, then ,             \n\n          (a) No light is transmitted             \n\n          (b) some light is transmitted            \n\n          (c) light may or may not be transmitted            \n\n          (d) exactly 50% light is transmitted.  \n\nQ.4 When a plane polarized light passed through a half wave plate, the emergent Light is             \n\n          (a) elliptically polarized             \n\n          (b) plane polarized             \n\n          (c) a mixture of elliptically and circularly polarized             \n\n          (d) circularly polarized  \n\nQ.5 Circularly polarized light is produced if the amplitudes of the ordinary and extra ordinary rays are equal and there is a phase difference of            \n\n          (a) π             \n\n          (b) π /2            \n\n          (c) π /4             \n\n          (d) zero \n\nQ.6 When elliptically polarized light, after passing through quarter wave plate, is observed through a rotating Nicol, the emergent light would have shown.            \n\n          (a) the variation of intensity with minimum not zero            \n\n          (b) no variation in intensity            \n\n          (c) the variation of intensity with minimum zero             \n\n          (d) the intensity of the emergent  light is same \n\nQ. 7 When light is incident at Brewster angle            \n\n          (a) the refracted light is plane polarized            \n\n          (b) the reflected light is partially plane polarized            \n\n          (c) the refracted light Is circularly polarized            \n\n          (d) the reflected light is plane polarized \n\nQ.8 0n rotating the analyser, the intensity of emergent light varies between a maximum and minimum with zero, than light incident on the analyzer is:            \n\n          (a) plane polarized             \n\n          (b) unpolarized            \n\n          (c) partially plane polarized             \n\n          (d) circularly polarized  \n\nQ. 9 On rotating the analyzer, the intensity of emergent light varies between a maximum and minimum which is not zero, then the light incident on the analyzer :            \n\n          (a) plane polarized             \n\n          (b) unpolarized             \n\n          (c) partially plane polarized             \n\n          (d) circularly polarized   \n\nQ. 10 On rotating the analyzer, the intensity of emergent light does not vary, then the light incident on the analyser Is            \n\n          (a) either plane polarized or partially polarized            \n\n          (b) either unpolarized or circularly polarized            \n\n          (c) either partially polarized or elliptically polarized             \n\n          (d) only circularly polarized \n\nQ.11 On rotating the analyzer the intensity of the emergent light varies between maximum and minimum but does not fall to zero, then the light incident on analyzer is             \n\n          (a) circularly polarized             \n\n          (b) plane polarized             \n\n          (c) unpolarized             \n\n          (d) elliptically polarized  \n\nQ.12 Plane polarized light is incident on an analyzer. If the intensity of the emergent ray falls to three fourth, the angle of the axis of the analyzer with respect to the plane of vibration of incident polarized beam is :             \n\n          (a) 30°             \n\n          (b) 45°              \n\n          (c) 60°             \n\n          (d) 0°  \n\nQ.13 To analyze a plane polarized lights an analyzer is rotated. In one complete rotation of the analyzer the following phenomenon occurs_             \n\n          (a) one complete extinction             \n\n          (b) one brightness and two times total darkness             \n\n          (c) two time brightness and one time total darkness             \n\n          (d) two time brightness and two time darkness  \n\nQ.14 An unpolarized beam of intensity 2a^2 passes through a polaroid. The intensity of emergent plane polarized light is             \n\n          (a) a^2              \n\n          (b) 2a^2              \n\n          (c) √2  a^2              \n\n          (d) a^2/2    \n\nQ.15 The axis of two Nicol prisms are parallel to one another. One of the two nicols is rotated through an angle of 60°. The ratio of the intensity of transmitted light before and after rotation is :            \n\n          (a) 1 : 2             \n\n          (b) 2 : 1             \n\n          (c) 4 : 1             \n\n          (d) 1 : 4  \n\nQ. 16 Two plane polarized beams of equal amplitudes having a phase difference of π/2, are mutually perpendicular. The superposition of these two beams results is :            \n\n          (a) plane polarized             \n\n          (b) circularly polarized            \n\n          (c) Elliptically polarized             \n\n          (d) partially plane polarized  \n\nQ.17 Polarized light can produced by            \n\n          (a) reflection             \n\n          (b) refraction            \n\n          (c) double refraction             \n\n          (d) all of them  \n\nQ.18 Polarization cannot occur in :            \n\n          (a) Light waves             \n\n          (b) X-rays            \n\n          (c)radio waves             \n\n          (d) sound waves  \n\nQ.19 Which of the following statements indicate that the light waves are transverse ?            \n\n          (a) Light waves can travel in vacuum            \n\n          (b) Light wave shows interference            \n\n          (c) Light waves can be polarized            \n\n          (d) Light waves can be diffracted \n\nQ.20 Biaxial crystal among the following is :            \n\n          (a) Quartz            \n\n          (b) Calcite            \n\n          (c) Tourmaline            \n\n          (d) Selenite \n\nQ.21 Ordinary light incident on a glass slab at the polarizing angle is refracted in glass and suffers a deviation of 22°. The value of the angle of refraction In glass in this case is             \n\n          (a) 68°              \n\n          (b) 56°             \n\n          (c) 21°              \n\n          (d) 34°   \n\nQ.22 When unpolarised light enters a doubly refracting crystal, we get two refracted rays called ordinary ray (O-ray) and extraordinary rays (E-ray).  Which of the following statement is true ?            \n\n          (a) Only O-ray polarized             \n\n          (b) Only E-ray polarized             \n\n          (c) Both O and E ray are polarized             \n\n          (d) Neither O-ray nor E-ray is polarized \n\nQ.23 Unpolarized light can be converted into a partially polarized or plane polarized by several processes. Which of the following doesn’t do that?             \n\n          (a) Reflection             \n\n          (b) Diffraction            \n\n          (c) Double refraction            \n\n          (d) Scattering \n\nQ.24 Which one is the example of biaxial crystal?             \n\n          (a) Sodium chloride             \n\n          (b) Tourmaline             \n\n          (c) Quartz             \n\n          (d) Aragonite \n\nQ.25 Two polarizing sheets have two polarizing directions parallel so that intensity of the transmitted light is maximum. If the intensity is to drop by one half, then either 0f the two sheets must be turned by            \n\n          (a) ± 30° and ± 135°             \n\n          (b) ± 45° and ± 120°            \n\n          (c) ± 30° and ± 120°             \n\n          (d) ± 45° and ± 135°  \n\nQ.26 If ‘ t ’ is the minimum thickness of a quarter wave plate needed to convert unpolarized light of wavelength 480 nm to circularly polarized light then the corresponding thickness of a quarter wave plate the wavelength 600 nm is,            \n\n          (a) 0.50 t             \n\n          (b) 0.75 t             \n\n          (c) 1.25 t             \n\n          (d) 1.44 t  \n\nQ.27 A beam of light is incident on a glass plate at an angle of incidence 60°. The reflected ray is polarized. What is the angle of refraction when angle of incidence is 45°?            \n\n          (a) 30°             \n\n          (b) 60°             \n\n          (c) sin^-1 (1 /√6)             \n\n          (d) sin^-1 (1 /√3)  \n\nQ.28 A mixture of unpolarized and circularly polarized light is passed through a quarter wave plate and then through an analyzer. As the analyser is rotated             \n\n          (a) there will be no variation in intensity             \n\n          (b) there are maxima and minima in intensity with Imin = 0             \n\n          (c) there are maxima and minima in intensity with Imin ≠ 0             \n\n          (d) The result depends on the orientation of the quarter wave plate \n\nQ.29 What happens to O-ray and E-ray, if they travel along the optic axis             \n\n          (a) both rays travel with same velocity             \n\n          (b) O-ray travels faster than E-ray             \n\n          (c) E-ray travels faster than O ray             \n\n          (d) none of them \n\nQ.30 How much phase change is introduced by a quarter wave plate between O-ray and E-ray             \n\n          (a) π             \n\n          (b) 2 π             \n\n          (c) π / 2             \n\n          (d) π / 4  \n\nQ.31 Dextrorotatory optically active substance rotates the plane of vibrations             \n\n          (a) In clockwise directions             \n\n          (b) In anti-clockwise direction             \n\n          (c) By 180°              \n\n          (d) None of them \n\nQ.32 Which are/is the example of uniaxial crystal ?             \n\n          (a) Calcite             \n\n          (b) Tourmaline             \n\n          (c) Quartz             \n\n          (d) All of them \n\nQ.33 What happens if the ordinary unpolarized light is passed through a uniaxial crystal?            \n\n          (a) Light split up into two rays             \n\n          (b) Light remains unaffected             \n\n          (c) Light is split into more than two rays             \n\n          (d) More of them  \n\nQ.34 The phenomenon of polarization takes place in             \n\n          (a) Longitudinal waves only             \n\n          (b) Transverse waves only             \n\n          (c) Both longitudinal and transverse waves             \n\n          (d) Neither longitudinal nor transverse waves  \n\nQ.35 A polarized beam is one in which            \n\n          (a) Electric vectors vibrate in all possible direction            \n\n          (b) Magnetic vector vibrates in all possible directions             \n\n          (c) Electric vector vibrates in a direction perpendicular to the direction of propagation of wave             \n\n          (d) None of these \n\nQ.36 Polarization cannot takes place in            \n\n          (a) X-rays             \n\n          (b) Light waves             \n\n          (c) Radio waves             \n\n          (d) Sound waves  \n\nQ.37 An unpolarized beam to transverse wave is one whose vibrations _             \n\n          (a) Are confined to a single plane             \n\n          (b) Occur in all directions perpendicular to the direction of propagation             \n\n          (c) Occur in all directions             \n\n          (d) Have not passed through a polaroid disc \n\nQ.38 A Calcite is placed over a dot on a piece of paper and rotated. On seeing through the calcite one will see            \n\n          (a) Tow rotating dots             \n\n          (b) One dot only             \n\n          (c) Two stationary dots            \n\n          (d) One dot rotating about the other  \n\nQ.39 The intensity of unpolarized light transmitted through the analyzer varies as the ____            \n\n          (a) Square of the cosine of the angle between the planes of transmission of polarizer and analyzer            \n\n          (b) Square of the sine of the angle between the planes of transmission of polarizer and analyzer            \n\n          (c) Tangent of the angle between the planes of transmission of polarizer and analyzer            \n\n          (d) Square of tangent of the angle between the planes of transmission of polarizer and analyzer \n\nQ.40 Optically active substance among the following is             \n\n          (a) Tourmaline             \n\n          (b) Quart             \n\n          (c) Calcite             \n\n          (d) Sodium chloride \n\nQ.41 When a ray of unpolarized light is incident in a directions perpendicular to the optic axis of a calcite crystal, then O-ray and E-ray travel             \n\n          (a) Along the different directions with same velocity            \n\n          (b) Along the same directions with same velocity            \n\n          (c) Along the same directions with different velocity            \n\n          (d) Along the different directions with different velocity \n\nQ.42 Ordinary light incident on a glass slab of the polarizing angle is refracted in glass and suffers a deviation of 22°, the value of the angle of refraction in glass in the case is             \n\n          (a) 68°             \n\n          (b) 21°             \n\n          (c) 56°             \n\n          (d) 34°  \n\nQ.43 Nicol prism is based on the phenomenon of             \n\n          (a) Reflection             \n\n          (b) Refraction             \n\n          (c) Double refraction             \n\n          (d) Scattering  \n\nQ.44 When a plane polarized light is passes through a half wave plate, the emergent light is            \n\n          (a) Plane polarized             \n\n          (b) Circularly polarized             \n\n          (c) Elliptically polarized             \n\n          (d) A mixture of elliptically and circularly polarized \n\nQ.45 A beam of light is passed through a polaroid and the latter is rotated with the light beam as axis. The intensity of the emergent light varies between maxima and a minimum. Then the light used as             \n\n          (a) A mixture of elliptically and unpolarized light             \n\n          (b) Elliptically polarized only             \n\n          (c) Neither \n\n          (a) nor \n\n          (b)             \n\n          (d) Either            \n\n          (a) or            \n\n          (b) \n\nQ.46 When a plane polarized light is incident on a quarter wave plate with its vibrations making an angle of 45° with the optic axis, the emergent light is             \n\n          (a) Circularly polarized             \n\n          (b) Plane polarized             \n\n          (c) Elliptically polarized             \n\n          (d) A mixture of circularly and elliptically polarized  \n\nQ.47 Elliptically polarized light is produced if the amplitudes of the extraordinary rays are unequal and there is a phase difference of             \n\n          (a) π             \n\n          (b) π /4             \n\n          (c) π /2             \n\n          (d) zero  \n\nQ.48 When a circularly polarized light, after passing through quarter wave plate is examined through a rotating Nicol, the emergent light would have shown             \n\n          (a) The variation of intensity from maximum to minimum (≠ 0)            \n\n          (b) The variation of intensity from maximum to minimum (= 0)            \n\n          (c) No variation in intensity            \n\n          (d) The intensity of incident and emergent light is same \n\nQ.49 The substances that show the phenomenon of optical rotation are said to be___            \n\n          (a) Optically inactive            \n\n          (b) Polaroid            \n\n          (c) Crystals            \n\n          (d) Optically active \n\nQ.50 Choose the incorrect statement. The amount of rotation of the plane of polarization is            \n\n          (a) Directly proportional to the concentration of the solution            \n\n          (b) Least for violet and greatest for red            \n\n          (c) Approximately inversely proportional to the square of the wavelength            \n\n          (d) Directly proportional to the length of the optically active substance "
            android:textColor="#000000"
            android:textSize="15dp"
            android:id="@+id/mcq_text4"
            android:paddingTop="15dp"
            android:typeface="normal"
            android:layout_below="@+id/spinner5"/>
</RelativeLayout>
    </ScrollView>