<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ScrollView
    xmlns:android="http://schemas.android.com/apk/res/android"
    android:id="@+id/scroll7"
    android:layout_height="wrap_content"
    android:layout_width="match_parent"
    android:background="@drawable/bg12">
<RelativeLayout xmlns:android="http://schemas.android.com/apk/res/android"
    xmlns:tools="http://schemas.android.com/tools" android:layout_width="match_parent"
    android:layout_height="match_parent" android:paddingLeft="@dimen/activity_horizontal_margin"
    android:paddingRight="@dimen/activity_horizontal_margin"
    android:paddingTop="@dimen/activity_vertical_margin"
    android:paddingBottom="@dimen/activity_vertical_margin"
    tools:context="com.horizon.abhijit.easycs1.chap2_mcq"
    android:background="@drawable/bg12">
    <Spinner
        android:layout_width="match_parent"
        android:layout_height="50dp"
        android:id="@+id/spinner1"
        android:layout_alignParentTop="true"
        android:layout_centerHorizontal="true"
        android:entries="@array/spinner_item2"
        android:layout_marginTop="10dp"
        android:background="@drawable/bg29" />
    <TextView
        android:layout_width="wrap_content"
        android:layout_height="wrap_content"
        android:id="@+id/mcq_text2"
        android:text="Q. 1 A diffraction pattern is obtained using a beam of red light. What happens if the red light is replaced by blue light ?           \n\n          (a)No change  b)Diffraction bands become narrower and crowded together  \n\n          (c)Diffraction bands become broader and further apart  \n\n          (d)Diffraction bands disappear.  \n\nQ. 2 In a Fraunhofer diffraction at a circular aperture, the radius of central disc is  \n\n          (a)independent of the diameter of aperture.  \n\n          (b)large as the diameter of aperture is large.  \n\n          (c)small as the diameter of aperture is large.  \n\n          (d)none of these  \n\nQ. 3 Maximum number of orders available with a grating is  \n\n          (a)directly proportional to the wavelength  \n\n          (b)inversely proportional to the grating element  \n\n          (c)independent of grating element  \n\n          (d)directly proportional to the grating element.  \n\nQ. 4 The resolving power of a grating  \n\n          (a)increases as the total number of lines on the grating increases  \n\n          (b)increases as the total number of lines on the grating decreases  \n\n          (c)increases as the order of spectrum decreases  \n\n          (d)increases as the grating element decreases  \n\nQ. 5 In a plane transmission grating, as the number of slits increased, the maxima become        	\n\n          (a)less brighter and much narrower                       	\n\n          (b)less brighter and less narrower           \n\n          (c)much brighter and less narrower              	\n\n          (d)much brighter and much narrower  \n\nQ. 6 The bending property of light at the sharp edge of the obstacle is known as                \n\n          (a)Interference  \n\n          (b)Dispersion                	\n\n          (c)Diffraction            	\n\n          (d)Polarisation  \n\nQ. 7 The phenomenon of diffraction of light can be observed if the size of the obstacle in path of the rays is of the order of                    	\n\n          (a)1 mm         	\n\n          (b)10-4 mm                  \n\n          (c)0.1 mm  \n\n          (d)1 cm  \n\nQ. 8 The conditions for observing Fraunhoffer diffraction from a single slit is that the light wave front incident on the slit must be                 \n\n          (a)Spherical  \n\n          (b)Plane  \n\n          (c)Cylindrical  \n\n          (d)Elliptical  \n\nQ. 9 In the diffraction pattern due to a single slit, the width of the central maximum,             \n\n          (a)with red light is less than with violet light.                \n\n          (b)with red light is more than with violet light.               \n\n          (c)with red light is equal to with violet light.             \n\n          (d)none of these.  \n\nQ. 10 In the diffraction pattern due to a single slit, the width of the central maximum will be       	\n\n          (a)greater for narrow slit                  \n\n          (b)less for narrow slit                 \n\n          (c)greater for wide slit                  \n\n          (d)less for wide slit  \n\nQ. 11 Consider Fraunhoffer diffraction pattern obtained with a single slit at normal incidence. At the angular position of the first diffraction minimum, the phase difference in radians between the wavelets from the opposite edges of the slit is                 \n\n          (a)π/4                  \n\n          (b)π/2                 \n\n          (c)2π                  \n\n          (d)π  \n\nQ. 12 In Fraunhoffer diffraction at a single slit the width of the slit is b. Screen is at a distance D from the slit. If slit width b is decreased further, the width of central maximum will                 \n\n          (a)increase.                 \n\n          (b)decrease.                 \n\n          (c)remains unchanged.                 \n\n          (d)may increase or decrease depending on the initial width.  \n\nQ. 13 The tip of a needle does not give a sharp image on the screen. This is due to the fact          	\n\n          (a)Interference                  \n\n          (b)diffraction                 \n\n          (c)polarization                  \n\n          (d)refraction  \n\nQ. 14 Yellow light is used in a single slit diffraction experiment with slit width of 0.6 mm. If the yellow light is replaced by X-rays, then the observed pattern will reveal          	 \n\n          (a)that the central maximum has become narrower.                 \n\n          (b)more number of fringes.                 \n\n          (c)no diffraction pattern.                 \n\n          (d)less number of fringes.  \n\nQ. 15 Diffraction effects are more pronounced or easier to notice in the case of sound waves than in the case of light waves because                 \n\n          (a)sound travels faster than light                 \n\n          (b)sound waves have a smaller wavelength.                 \n\n          (c)sound waves are longitudinal.                 \n\n          (d)sound waves are of longer wavelength.  \n\nQ. 16 In a plane transmission grating, the intensity of principal maximum                 \n\n          (a)increases as the number of slits increases.                 \n\n          (b)decreases as the number of slits increases.                 \n\n          (c)remains constant as the number of slits increases.                 \n\n          (d)none of these.  \n\nQ. 17 In a plane transmission grating, the intensity of secondary maxima                 \n\n          (a)increases as the number of slits increases.                 \n\n          (b)decreases as the number of slits increases.                 \n\n          (c)remains constant as the number of slits increases.                 \n\n          (d)none of these.  \n\nQ. 18 If N is the total number of rulings on the grating, m is the order of spectrum and λ is the wavelength of light used, then resolving power of grating is given by,                 \n\n          (a) Nmλ                 \n\n          (b)Nλ/m                \n\n          (c)Nm            \n\n          (d) N/m  \n\nQ. 19 A grating which would be more suitable for constructing a spectrometer for the visible and ultra violet regions, should have        	 \n\n          (a)100 lines/cm                  \n\n          (b)1000 lines/cm                 \n\n          (c)10,000 lines/cm                  \n\n          (d)106 lines/cm  \n\nQ. 20 In a plane diffraction grating, the width of principal maximum,                 \n\n          (a)increases as the number of slits increases.                 \n\n          (b)decreases as the number of slits increases.                 \n\n          (c)remains constant as the number of slits increases.                 \n\n          (d)none of these.  \n\nQ. 21 In a plane diffraction grating, the angle of diffraction is                 \n\n          (a)directly proportional to the wavelength.          	\n\n          (b)inversely proportional to the wavelength.                 \n\n          (c)directly proportional to the square root of the wavelength.                 \n\n          (d)inversely proportional to the square root of the wavelength.  \n\nQ. 22 Which one of the following plane transmission grating of width W and number of lines per cm N will have the maximum resolving power in the first order.                 \n\n          (a)W = 1 cm, N = 5000                  \n\n          (b)W = 0.5 cm, N = 4000                 \n\n          (c)W = 2 cm, N = 2400                  \n\n          (d)W = 3 cm, N = 1500  \n\nQ. 23 Dispersive power of a grating can be defined as         	 \n\n          (a)increase of angle of refraction w.r.t. change in wavelength.                 \n\n          (b)increase of angle of incidence w.r.t. change in wavelength.      	\n\n          (c)increase of angle of diffraction w.r.t. change in wavelength.                 \n\n          (d)None of these.  \n\nQ. 24 Which of the following statement is incorrect? The dispersive power of a grating_      	\n\n          (a)is directly proportional to the order of the spectrum.                 \n\n          (b)is inversely proportional to the grating element.                 \n\n          (c)is directly proportional to the wavelength.                 \n\n          (d)is inversely proportional to the cosine of the angle of diffraction.  \n\nQ. 25 A parallel beam of light wavelength 600 nm gets diffracted by a single slit of width 0.2 mm. The angular divergence of the first maxima of diffracted light is                 \n\n          (a)6.3 × 10- 3 rad.                  \n\n          (b)3 × 10- 3 rad.                 \n\n          (c)4.5 × 10- 2 rad.                  \n\n          (d)9 × 10- 2 rad.  \n\nQ. 26 In far field diffraction pattern of single slit under polychromatic illumination, the first minimum with the wavelength λ1 is found to be coincident with the third minimum at λ2. Then the relationship between these two wavelength is                 \n\n          (a)3λ1 = 0.3 λ2                  \n\n          (b)3λ1 = λ2                 \n\n          (c)λ1 = 3λ2                  \n\n          (d)0.3λ1 = 3λ2  \n\nQ. 27 According to Rayleigh’s criterion of resolution, the two spectral lines of equal intensity are just resolved when the central maximum of the diffraction pattern due to one falls          	\n\n          (a)on the central maximum of the diffraction pattern of other.                 \n\n          (b)on the secondary maximum of the diffraction pattern of other.                 \n\n          (c)on the first minimum of the diffraction pattern of other.                 \n\n          (d)None of these.  \n\nQ. 28 In single slit diffraction, the first diffraction minima is observed of an angle of 30?, when the light of wavelength 500 mm is used. The width of the slit is                 \n\n          (a)5 × 10- 5 cm                  \n\n          (b)2.5 × 10- 5 cm                 \n\n          (c)10 × 10- 5 cm                  \n\n          (d)1.25 × 10- 5 cm  \n\nQ. 29 In Fraunhoffer diffraction the wave front undergoing diffraction has to be                 \n\n          (a)Spherical                  \n\n          (b)cylindrical                 \n\n          (c)elliptical                  \n\n          (d)plane  \n\nQ. 30 In a single slit experiment if the slit width is reduced         	 \n\n          (a)the fringes becomes brighter                 \n\n          (b)the fringes becomes narrower                 \n\n          (c)the fringes becomes wider                 \n\n          (d)the colour of the fringes change  \n\nQ. 31 Instead of red colour source, if blue colour source is used in single slit experiment       	\n\n          (a)the diffraction pattern does not change.                 \n\n          (b)the diffraction bands become wider.                 \n\n          (c)the diffraction pattern becomes narrower and crowded together.                 \n\n          (d)the diffraction pattern disappears.  \n\nQ. 32 The diffraction pattern of a single slit consists of          	 \n\n          (a)wider dark band at the center with alternate bright and dark bands or either side                \n\n          (b)narrow bright band at the center with alternate dark and bright bands of equal intensity on either side                 \n\n          (c)wider bright band at the center with alternate dark and bright bands of equal intensity on either side                 \n\n          (d)wider and brighter band at the center with alternate dark and bright bands of decreasing intensity on either side.  \n\nQ. 33 The diffraction pattern due to circular aperture consists of      	 \n\n          (a)a bright central disc surrounded by alternate dark and bright concentric rings        	\n\n          (b)a dark central disc surrounded by alternate dark and bright concentric rings                 \n\n          (c)a bright central disc only                 \n\n          (d)a bright central disc surrounded by alternate dark and bright concentric rings with equal spacing between the rings.  \n\nQ. 34 In circular aperture diffraction, when a lens of focal length 1 m is used to focus the diffraction pattern on the screen, if 600 nm is the wavelength of the light and 1 mm is the radius of the Airy’s disc, then the diameter of the aperture is      \n\n          (a)0.6 cm                  \n\n          (b)0.6 mm                  \n\n          (c)0.167 mm                  \n\n          (d)0.167 cm  \n\nQ. 35 A parallel beam of monochromatic light falls normally on a plane diffraction grating having 5000 lines/cm. A second order spectral line is diffracted through an angle of 30°. The wavelength of light is                 \n\n          (a)5 × 10-7 cm                	  \n\n          (b)5 × 10-6 cm                 \n\n          (c)5 × 10-5 cm                  \n\n          (d)5 × 10-4 cm  \n\nQ. 36 A beam of light of wavelength 600 m falls of a single slit 0.1 mm wide and the resulting diffraction pattern is observed on a screen 2m away. The distance between the first dark fringes on either side of the central bright fringe is                 \n\n          (a)2.4 mm                  \n\n          (b)1.2 cm                  \n\n          (c)1.2 mm                  \n\n          (d)2.4 cm  \n\nQ. 37 A screen is at a distance of 2 m from a narrow slit illuminated by light of wavelength 600 nm. The first minimum lies 5 mm on either side of the central maximum. The width of slit is                 \n\n          (a)0.024 mm                  \n\n          (b)0.24 mm                  \n\n          (c)2.4 mm                  \n\n          (d)24 mm  \n\nQ. 38 A single slit is illuminated with a parallel beam of μ = 500 nm. The emergent beam has divergence of 30°.The size of the aperture is                 \n\n          (a)1 μm                  \n\n          (b)10 μm                  \n\n          (c)2.5 μm                  \n\n          (d)25 μm  \n\nQ. 39 When white light is incident on a diffraction grating, the light diffracted more will be        	\n\n          (a)blue                  \n\n          (b)yellow                  \n\n          (c)violet                  \n\n          (d)red  \n\nQ. 40 A grating is able to resolve two very close spectral lines of wavelength 5890 Å and 5896 Å in its first order diffraction. The resolving power of the grating is                 \n\n          (a)close to 6000                  \n\n          (b)close to 1000                 \n\n          (c)close to 3000                  \n\n          (d)close to 12,000>  \n\nQ. 41 If 1000 is the resolving power of a grating in the first order, its resolving power in second order is given by                 \n\n          (a)500                  \n\n          (b)1000                 \n\n          (c)2000                  \n\n          (d)none of these  \n\nQ. 42 The resolving power of a microscope is given by,                 \n\n          (a) (2N.A)/λ0                 \n\n          (b)   2/(λ0(N.A))                 \n\n          (c) (2.λ0)/(N.A)                \n\n          (d) (N.A)/(2.λ0)  \n\nQ. 43 In Fresnel diffraction                 \n\n          (a)source of light is kept at infinite distance from the aperture                 \n\n          (b)source of light is kept at finite distance from the aperture                 \n\n          (c)convex lens is used           	\n\n          (d)aperture width is selected so that it can act as a point source  \n\nQ. 44 Significant diffraction of x-rays can be obtained                \n\n          (a)be a single slit                  \n\n          (b)by a double slit                 \n\n          (c)by an atomic crystal                  \n\n          (d)none of these  \n\nQ. 45 A parallel beam of light of wavelength 600 nm gets diffracted by a single slit of width 0.2 mm the angular divergence of the first maxima of diffracted light is                 \n\n          (a)6 × 10-3 rad                  \n\n          (b)3 × 10-3 rad                 \n\n          (c)4.5 × 10-3 rad                  \n\n          (d)9 × 10-2 rad.  \n\nQ. 46 The number of rulings (N) in grating is made larger, then                 \n\n          (a)the principal and secondary (all) maxima will become sharp and intense                 \n\n          (b)the principal and secondary (all) maxima will become faint and wide                 \n\n          (c)the principal maxima will become intense and sharp, while secondary maxima become weaker                 \n\n          (d)the principal maxima become weaker while secondary maxima become sharp and intense.  \n\nQ. 47 Diffraction effects are more pronounced or easier to notice in the case of sound waves than in the case of light waves because                 \n\n          (a)sound travels faster than light                 \n\n          (b)sound waves have a smaller wavelength                 \n\n          (c)source waves are of longer wavelength                 \n\n          (d)sound waves are longitudinal  \n\nQ. 48 Sunlight filtering through a tree often makes circular patches on the ground because          	\n\n          (a)the space through which light penetrates is round                 \n\n          (b)of the scattering of light                 \n\n          (c)of the diffraction phenomenon                 \n\n          (d)of the interference phenomenon  \n\nQ. 49 Consider Fraunhoffer diffraction pattern obtained with a single slit at normal incidence. At the angular position of the first diffraction minimum the phase difference (in radians) between the wavelets from the opposite edges of the slit is :                 \n\n          (a)π/4                  \n\n          (b)π/2                  \n\n          (c)π                  \n\n          (d)2 π  \n\nQ. 50 A parallel beam of monochromatic of wavelength ? passes through a slit of width  b. After passing through the slit the light is incident of a distant screen. The angular width of the central maxima is                 \n\n          (a)2 λ/b radians                 \n\n          (b)λ/b radians                 \n\n          (c)2 λ/b degrees                 \n\n          (d)λ/b degrees  \n\nQ. 51 The diffraction of light at a single slit is maximum, when following condition is satisfied.       	\n\n          (a)Width of the slit is comparable with the wavelength of the light used.                 \n\n          (b)Width of the slit is more than the wavelength of the light used.                 \n\n          (c)Width of slit is less than the wavelength of the light used.                 \n\n          (d)None of these  \n\nQ. 52 In the diffraction pattern due to single slit of width a, with incident light of wavelength λ, with angle of diffraction θ, The condition for the first minimum is                 \n\n          (a)λ sin θ = a                 \n\n          (b)a cos θ = λ                 \n\n          (c)a sin θ = λ                 \n\n          (d)λ cos θ = a  \n\nQ. 53 In Fraunhoffer diffraction, the diffracted wave front is                 \n\n          (a)Plane                 \n\n          (b)Spherical                 \n\n          (c)Cylindrical                 \n\n          (d)None of these  \n\nQ. 54 Choose the correct statement, for Fraunhoffer diffraction                 \n\n          (a)The initial phase of secondary wavelets is same at all points in the plane of aperture.           	\n\n          (b)The initial phase of secondary wavelets is different at different points in the plane of aperture.                 \n\n          (c)Mathematical treatment is not easy.                 \n\n          (d)It has less applications in designing optical instruments.  \n\nQ. 55 The central fringe in diffraction pattern is always.                 \n\n          (a)bright                 \n\n          (b)dark                 \n\n          (c)difficult to say                 \n\n          (d)None of these  \n\nQ. 56 Choose the correct statement                 \n\n          (a)The diffraction fringes are always equally spaced.                 \n\n          (b)The diffraction fringes are never equally spaced.                 \n\n          (c)In diffraction pattern only bright fringes all equally spaced.                 \n\n          (d)In diffraction pattern only dark fringes are equally spaced.  \n\nQ. 57 Choose the correct statement                 \n\n          (a)In diffraction pattern minima are not perfectly dark, so the contrast between fringes is not good.                 \n\n          (b)In diffraction pattern minima are perfectly dark so, the contrast between fringes is good.                 \n\n          (c)In diffraction pattern minima are perfectly dark so, the contrast between fringes is not good.                 \n\n          (d)In diffraction pattern minima are not perfectly dark, so the contrast between fringes is good.  \n\nQ. 58 In Fraunhoffer diffraction at a circular aperture the radius of Airy’s disc is given by        	\n\n          (a)  Y=fd/λ                \n\n          (b) Y=λ/fd                 \n\n          (c) Y=λ/d                 \n\n          (d) Y=λf/d  \n\nQ. 59 The condition of minima for grating                 \n\n          (a)N (a + b) sin θ = mλ                 \n\n          (b)(a + b) sin θ = mλ                 \n\n          (c)(a + b) sin θ = m N λ                 \n\n          (d)N (a + b) cos θ = m λ  \n\nQ. 60 Diffraction of light will be maximum when wavelength of light is                 \n\n          (a)Comparable to the width of the slit                 \n\n          (b)Greater than the width of the slit                 \n\n          (c)Less than the width of the slit                 \n\n          (d)None of these  \n\nQ. 61 Type of diffraction is used mostly for industrial applications.                 \n\n          (a)Fraunhoffer                 \n\n          (b)Fresnel                 \n\n          (c)Both \n\n          (a) and \n\n          (b)                 \n\n          (d)Either \n\n          (a) or \n\n          (b)  \n\nQ. 62 Calculate the angle at which first order minima appears for a single slit of width 0.1 mm and wavelength of light is 5890 Å                 \n\n          (a)0.33 degree                 \n\n          (b)0.40 degree                 \n\n          (c)0.30 degree                 \n\n          (d)0.50 degree  \n\nQ. 63 The intensity of first secondary maxima during diffraction of light due to single slit compared to central maxima is                 \n\n          (a)100%                  \n\n          (b)0.045%                 \n\n          (c)0.016%                  \n\n          (d)0.0083%  "
        android:layout_below="@+id/spinner1"
        android:layout_marginTop="15dp"
        android:textColor="#000000"
        android:typeface="serif" />
</RelativeLayout>
</ScrollView>